Uh they say here we conjecture that there exists
an orthogonal polygon of 46 unit squares that
admits to fold these three boxes. So there's
not people who watch my videos were able to
disprove this conjecture as false and discover a
whole new net that even the best mathematicians
at MIT couldn't find. Ah it's so ridiculous.
Welcome to this year's best breaking mass news.
This video is sponsored by Jane Street's 2027
paid internships. Applications open now. Way
back at the end of uh the year of our Lord 2022,
the smallest known net that could fold into three
different cuboids had an area of 532. But people
who watch these videos found a net with an area
of 106. That's so much smaller. It's ridiculous.
And I will explain the backstory. If you haven't
seen the previous video, don't panic. Why this is
amazing, what we're going to do next. But I need
to say not AI found completely by humans. And
I just want to put a little historical marker
down right now in the middle of 2026 that in 2
months we've gone from me making a video saying
this is incredible a large language model found
some maths to me having to say, "Oh my goodness,
we found some maths that wasn't done
by a large language model." You know,
life moves fast. What we're talking
about here. Oh, and hello new people.
Thanks for sticking with me. Uh, nets that
fold into multiple different boxes. This
is the animated gift that started this whole
thing. I always thought if you unfolded a box,
a cuboid into a net, you fold the net
back up, you get the same box back. No,
you can have the same net that folds into multiple
cuboids. And the smallest such one has an area
of 22 squares and folds into these two boxes. But
that's not the only one. Turns out there are 2,263
of these 22 area nets that have that property.
And so I thought just to mix it up because this
is the second video now in apparently a series
is I've got the website here that has all 2000
look at them all all laid out in HTML or uh 2263
of these nets. So I figure I'll pick one at random
and I'll build two copies and we'll fold them into
two different boxes. So, let's go with this one.
That one. Let's do it. Oh, that's a fun one. So,
the rule with these is that you don't have to cut
any of the edges that line up in the net, but the
corners aren't fixed. So, this next row is going
to have I'll do these in stripes. It's going to
have one there, but those corners aren't fused.
But that's that's all going to work out. So, here
we go. Maybe I can make both of them at the same
time if I build them one on top of the other.
[laughter] Uh, genius or foolish. Let's find out.
Maybe this way is easier. There we are.
Upside down. Two identical nets. Now I've
just got to work out how to fold two copies
of the same net into two different cuboids.
Aka the easy bit. If I just start curling
this up, it should just become a shape,
right? This No. What if that was there? Oh, hang
on. No. Yes. Ah, right. [music] That can go there.
So, I'm not undoing and redoing anything. I'm just
joining edges together [music] as if I was taping.
But I learned last time that takes forever. As
if I was taping a net together. [music] One by
one by five. And that goes there. No, no. Oh, hang
on. That would fit 1x 2x3. These both have an area
of 22 and they can unfold into the same net. And
they can do that 2263 different ways. And if you
think about it, I mean, now now I've joined it up,
you can't tell the difference between the original
hinge joins and the new ones I've just made.
But where I to want to undo this, I have so many
choices about exactly which ones I undo until it's
planer, until it's flat on the ground. And that's
that's the combinatorics I get you. When you
start undoing cuboids into their nets, you just
have so many choices, which makes searching for
these solutions both on one hand very difficult,
but on the flip side, it means there can be
a lot of them. There's over 2,000 of these.
So the obvious next question is if you can find
a net that folds into two different cuboids,
is there a net that folds into three
different cuboids? And for a very long time,
ever since 2015, it was known that that was
possible. But the smallest net ever found had
an area of 532 squares. And last time I got
three copies and I put them together. [music]
You know what? I don't know if the people
who wrote the paper would have ever bothered
actually making these. So I very easily could
be the first human who ever folded the same net
into three distinct shapes only with orthogonal
folds. I mean, conceivably someone else might
have done it. The author's working on the
paper or someone who read it since then,
but that was a lot of faf. But now we have a
brand new discovery of a much smaller net that
does the job. So, forget these honestly things
that fold into two different cuboids. We can fold
into three different cuboids. And of course, we
have to do it with an actual piece of paper. So,
oh, here it comes. So here we have our newly
discovered net. And while 106 squares is very
small compared to the previous record holder,
it is given we've printed these at a reasonable
size. It is still a very big piece of paper. But
don't worry, I'm, you know, if nothing but not
dedicated to physically cutting these things out.
Um, as dedicated as I am to ridiculous sight gags,
I now have three identical copies. We brought the
other two in off camera. And you can see they're
they're all exactly the same. We've just done
them in different colors. You can kind of tell
them apart. And what I'm going to do is fold each
one of these up differently to end up with three
distinct cuboids. Actually, I'll put two of
them down there. We'll do Let's do the green
one first. And as is tradition, I'm [music] just
going to tape it together. It's not perfect, FYI,
just in case you were fooled by my incredible
assembly. But there it is. There is the first
of three cuboids. Oh no. This one has a real 1x 2
by N vibe to it. Okay, I think that's the end. So,
if I stick the end, I can turn around and go back
the other way. And while I'm doing this, it's a
good time to thank the sponsor of this video, Jane
Street. So, they're a quantitive trading firm and
applications for their internships next year,
2027. Uh, the applications are now open. There
aren't many prerequisites as well. Jane Street
internships are just looking for people who are
intellectually curious and enjoy collaborative
problem solving. Oh, and at the moment with an
extra focus on cutting edge machine learning
applications, the applicants can be anywhere
in the world. Last year we had interns from over
117 different schools across 32 countries. And
we're looking forward to similar numbers this year
going between the Hong Kong, New York, London, and
now Singapore offices. Oh. Um, yeah. And during
your internship, you will be able to meaningfully
contribute to projects as well as learning from
their their highly enthusiastic, passionate staff
that come from a very wide range of academic and
industrial backgrounds. [snorts] And finally,
you don't need any specific finance background.
Most people at J Street started exactly where
you were. They were just a curious individual
who got hooked on one of the topics available
at the internships. Be it quantitive trading,
machine learning, software engineering, research,
strategy, product, institutional sales, trading,
and more. You name it, they cover it. I mean,
as long as what you name pertains to quantitative
trading. So, thank you so much to Jane Street for
sponsoring this as well as so many of my other
videos. If the internship sounds like something
you would like to do or you know someone for
whom it might be appropriate, please do send
them the link that's in the description or scan
the QR code that's on the screen right now.
Thank you, Jane Street. Now, I better get back
to paying attention to this ridiculous cuboid.
Took a little more tape on the outside
than I appreciate, but second cuboid. So,
now we've got that one and that one. One more to
go. Just by sheer luck of the draw. Technically,
I've left the easy one till last
for some definition of easy.
Okay, [laughter] there. There it is. All right.
I was about to say not my best taping work,
but I am disproportionately proud of that
because even though it looks a little bit janky,
that was a tough folding tape. That might be
the most complex one I've done on the channel,
but there you are. That is uh 26 squares this
way by one by one for a total surface area
of 106. Uh back here, this one was 17 up and
down by 2x 1 for a total surface area of 106.
And then this one here, 8x 5x 1 for a total
surface area, you can work this out yourself,
of 106. So there you are. Three different cuboids
all folded from exactly the same net. The shape
that mathematicians couldn't find. The best
they could do is 532. But you, and I mean
literally you, people who watch these videos
found this one. And as for how that happened,
well, funny story. This is the 2013 paper that
started our adventure. Common developments,
which just means like nets that are the same of
three inongruent, so three different orthogonal
boxes, which I'll occasionally call boys and
orthogonal just means right angles, well behaved,
all that. I'm going to highlight Rahu, one of
the authors. We're going to meet them a couple
times. And everyone here is based at the Japan
Advanced Institute of Science and Technology.
And down here in the paper, uh there's the net.
There it is. That's the one that I cut out and
made last time. Area 532. This was the initial
announcement of that net, the world record for
a long time afterwards. And they raised the two
questions that over a decade later we solved.
Finding much smaller polygons would be future
work. They were correct. And in particular,
is there a common development of area 46 that can
fold into three boxes? And they happen to give the
sizes there. I just want to highlight down here.
These are a lot of the characters you'll see
repeating as well as the Japan Advanced Institute
of Science and Technology. Uh you got the domains
going on in here. In fact, we'll see Eric domain
a bunch. They're all at MIT. That's the other
major institution that's been heavily involved
in this work. Oh, and here you go. This paper,
there's Ruhigh kicking around. You've also got
the domains. Very excited about that. And here's
a deep standup mass cut. This is Zack. Zach is at
MIT and they designed the paper clip monstrosity
that Adam Savage and I struggled to build. The
next major milestone was 2022 when I released a
video on the subject. Now, a stand-up math video
coming out is always a major historical event,
but in this occasion, it's because I also reached
out to a bunch of nerds. Shout out to Landon,
Benjamin, and Stu, who all got heavily involved.
But I just basically emailed all the viewers who
previously had dramatically improved some code I'd
written. It's true. A viewer says, "One of you,
I'm holding you all collectively responsible,
took some terrible Python code of mine and made
it over 4 million% better, which is to say it
achieved the same thing, but faster." Yeah,
it jerks a lot of you. No, I'm kidding. I love
I love my viewers who get uh unduly involved and
so thanks to these three who really picked up the
net idea and ran with it. We didn't find anything
before my video came out. Afterwards, Michael
got involved. They actually put a comment on my
Patreon page saying that they had some ideas.
I put them in touch with the others. They all
started working on it in earnest. And then 2023,
Michael did it. Michael just found a 106 area net.
and they let me know by just emailing me a photo
of it. So, this just appeared in my inbox a brand
new bit of mathematics. No one to no one except
for the small squad of nerds who watch my videos
and me. I of course reached out to the folks at
MIT and in 2024 MIT got involved and huge thanks
to Alice, Jenny and Eric got involved, helped
organize the process, contributed new ideas. Jenny
particularly worked with Michael to tease out
some extra aspects of the mathematics involved.
And we also got Ruhigh. It's the whole it's the
dream team, the super group of mathematicians
because everyone had their actual you know real
research to be doing and day jobs in the case of
Michael. It took a while to work through all the
mathematics. uh but by 2025 we had the paper being
written up pretty much finished and then we had to
look for a place to get it published conferences
to go to and that's why in 2026 we are finally
announcing this breakthrough discovery and by
now you're probably thinking hang on a second
how did we even find this now it wasn't just
having more compute time and it wasn't just
making the code more efficient although both
those things did happen in fact those combined
is we're able to disprove 46 so we now know there
are no solutions with an area of 46. So we're
moving the lower bound up. But on top of that,
Michael had an extra insight into types of nets
that are more likely to have this property. So
we haven't done an exhaustive search at 106 or
below that, but we have found 40 distinct nets all
with an area of 106 that fold into three different
cuboids. And well, what Michael realized is that a
lot of the solutions are probably going to have a
one by one by n and one by one by n's have certain
properties in our final paper. Oh, and check out I
mean there's a mass vengers if I've ever seen them
assemble and polyomino nets is just saying squares
joined together on the edges. No funny business.
So you can see Michael's breakthrough down here in
the official diagram announcing this net and you
can see the different folding lines. So same net
but you do subtly different folds for the three
different cuboids. Here they are all overlaid.
If you think about the folding that gives you
the one by one by 26. You can see here there's
always batches of four squares. Four squares.
Four squares for every single horizontal row. And
this diagram has exactly four squares in a row.
And that's because each of these rolls up to form
a little band. And there's, you know, 26 of these
which forms a long tube. And then you got one at
each end for the caps. It's a very neat insight.
And we can show you how we built on this with
a slightly less complicated but equivalent type
of net. Okay. So, I'm just going to kind of hold
this one together. This is a 1x3x5. There's its
net. And if I unfold that, it also becomes a 1x
one by n. And I and as I roll it up, you notice,
wait a minute, as I'm rolling this, these are
all four. These are all like bands of four. And
that kind of makes sense because each one rolls
all the way around uh the one by one by end. So
each one just becomes another band this way and
you go all the way along and then you get the end
caps. And actually, if you unfold the net, that's
kind of obvious. And we've got a colored in one.
So, this was Michael's big insight is you end
up with basically stacked rows of four, which
I'll I'll fold them all out here. So, the single
one at the top and then we've colored them four,
four, four, four, four all the way down. And then
when you roll that up into your one by one by N,
all of these form colored stripes that go all
the way around. But then if we do it the other
way around, and this will take me a second
to um fold it up in the other orientation.
I'll make these files available. By the way,
it's kind of f like it's not obvious where
all the folds go as you may remember from when
I was doing the um much more complicated. Oh,
that goes out there. Uh 22 one earlier. There
we go. That goes there. That goes there.
Okay. So, I haven't taped it together, but you can
see those stripes now go the other way around on
the 1x 3x5. So, they've kind of each one combines
and and goes goes around it that way there. So,
the fact that we could reduce the search space
from just any old combinations of squares stuck
together to ones with these stripes that go in
different directions meant that it was searchable
and it meant that we were able to find this one.
And with one extra insight and a matrix, we could
find multitudes of these. Over here in the same
paper, you can see where Michael gave the exact
same example to show how the stripes when you got
your one by one then align up into a different
one. But that's not the only direction we took
it. These nets were excluding the caps on either
end. Every single row has four squares that forms
a complete band all the way around the cuboid are
called stacked nets. And we found a whole bunch
of these specifically as well as the kind of
canonical first one that was found. It turns out
there were 15 of them. We found 15 common stacked
nets. Now, a while ago, I promised 40. So, you're
thinking, where are the other 25? Well, it turns
out stack nets aren't the only option. Down here,
we have, check this out, right? So, we still have
the end caps, one of each. Every single row still
has four squares, but now they're not contiguous.
So, it can go down and come back up again. So
there's still four squares here that will form a
band, but it's not like before where they already
start joined together. So it's a more complicated
way of doing it. These are called simple phase
nets. And these provided the other 25. And once
you take out uh the ones that are equivalent
because they're like, you know, symmetric, you
know, they match up. So the 25 new nets were found
for a total of 40. Now there's loads more in this
paper, but I do want to um highlight this matrix.
This may be one of my favorite things that came
out of it. So if we go back to that simple phase
um one here, you can see actually there are seven
different possible options for each of the layers,
right? So you got seven uh different arrangements
of the four squares in a way such they can all
join together to form a complete, you know,
one piece net. And depending on what one you've
got above, there are a number of different ones in
different positions that you can put underneath.
And so this matrix is keeping track for any one of
those seven states above which ones can possibly
go underneath it. And you got that little 16 out
the front there. That's because the caps each
have four options each for where they can go.
So you can understand the space of all possible
combinations of these seven different layers
and the simple phase nets using this matrix.
I don't get like lost in the weeds here. Um,
but of course you got a matrix, you're going to
have an igon value. And the iggon value gives us a
sense of how fast the number of possible solutions
grows as you have more layers. Just one more
really nice bit of mathematics that came out in
the process of putting together this this. I mean,
I'm very proud of it. Phenomenal. And despite my
trivial contribution, Michael should be very proud
of this. Uh, what a paper. There is loads more
lovely mathematics in the paper. So, of course,
I will link to it in the description below, just
below the link to the Jane Street internships. Do
check those out. But what I love the most about
the paper is if you look at the author list,
everyone's here. The researchers from Japan, the
researchers from MIT, the people who bully me by
writing more efficient code and putting it in my
YouTube comments. Uh, Michael with his big insight
that he just put as a comment on Patreon. We got
producer Nicole and we got me. I'm now a co-author
on a paper with Eric Domain and it's thanks to the
phenomenal community of people who you like you're
great humans. You watch my videos and you get
involved. Speaking of getting involved, we still
got some open questions here, don't we? So, we
now know that 106 is possible for three different
cuboids. We know 46 is impossible. There's
a bunch of numbers between those two values.
probably like 59 of I'm not going to fence post
that live. But I am going to challenge you,
everyone watching this video. Can we find
a smaller one than 106? It probably exists.
Can we move the lower bound up some more? Almost
certainly. So, please do get involved. And I mean,
the big question is, is there a net that folds
into four different cuboids? I mean, almost
certainly yes. What size? We have no idea. When
are we going to find it? Well, if we extrapolate
from one data point, another four years. So,
everyone get onto it and I'll see you in 2030.